<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rant on cat /dev/random</title>
    <link>http://192.241.186.225/tags/rant/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rant on cat /dev/random</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 12:34:58 AST</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://192.241.186.225/tags/rant/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A Happy Accident</title>
      <link>http://192.241.186.225/articles/a-happy-accident/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 12:34:58 AST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://192.241.186.225/articles/a-happy-accident/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, I was pleasantly surprised to find an email by a correspondent of &lt;a href=&#34;http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/&#34;&gt;Economic Times&lt;/a&gt; (a leading newspaper in India) asking for permission to quote a comment I made on &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7698688&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; in the newspaper&amp;rsquo;s front page!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope they have India on their radar! It would be awesome for the Indian Startup scene to hear all those great speakers live!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;/images/et.jpg&#34;&gt; &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who knew that a comment on HN would end up on the front-page of a newspaper!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maciej on Matasano</title>
      <link>http://192.241.186.225/articles/maciej-on-matasano/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 12:34:58 AST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://192.241.186.225/articles/maciej-on-matasano/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just when you promise yourself that you are going to work on &lt;a href=&#34;http://csapp.cs.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;systems&lt;/a&gt; for a couple of weeks and not get diverted, you get to hear about new ways to kill time learning &lt;a href=&#34;http://cryptopals.com/&#34;&gt;crypto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a programmer, my core strengths have always been knowing how to apologize to users, and composing funny tweets. While I can hook up a web template to a database and make the squigglies come out right, I cannot efficiently sort something for you on a whiteboard, or tell you where to get a monad. From my vantage point, crypto looms as high as Mount Olympus. - Maciej Ceglowski on &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.pinboard.in/2013/04/the_matasano_crypto_challenges/&#34;&gt;Matasano Crypto Challenges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deal With It</title>
      <link>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-02-22-deal-with-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-02-22-deal-with-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hilarious fable on HN featuring the superhero Unix and its trusted sidekick - Vim!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ring ring ring&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;yeah, what&amp;rsquo;s up?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;ins&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nagios.org/&#34;&gt;Nagios&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/ins&gt; is paging, something with that code you pushed live a couple hours ago is throwing a fit&amp;hellip; looks like half the web cluster is on the verge of &lt;ins&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://help.ubuntu.com/community/SwapFaq/#What_is_swappiness_and_how_do_I_change_it.3F&#34;&gt;going to swap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;, can you look into it? asap!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Well, I&amp;rsquo;m on at the bus stop and won&amp;rsquo;t be near a computer for at least an hour&amp;hellip;yeah, I&amp;rsquo;ll sort it out, will text you when we can push fix live.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pulls out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.samsung.com/global/microsite/galaxynote3-gear/&#34;&gt;Note 3&lt;/a&gt;, shitty 3G coverage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;connects to VPN&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ssh into dev env with &lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.connectbot&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;connectbot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;switches to &lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.pocketworkstation.pckeyboard&#34;&gt;hackerkeyboard&lt;/a&gt; for input mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kb.iu.edu/data/acuy.html&#34;&gt;screen -dr dev&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ctrl+c&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;tail join IRC channel that dumps syslogs from production cluster&lt;/code&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:dbc271c6a37f1f7f89c8f6ceae38e912:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:dbc271c6a37f1f7f89c8f6ceae38e912:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;sees error&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ctrl+c&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;vim the/file/causing/the/unexpected/problem&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fix the problem&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;code&gt;:wq&lt;/code&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:dbc271c6a37f1f7f89c8f6ceae38e912:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:dbc271c6a37f1f7f89c8f6ceae38e912:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% highlight bash %}
git stash
git pull
git stash apply
git commit
git push
{% endhighlight %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ctrl+d&lt;/em&gt;, exit&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sends text message &amp;ldquo;good to go!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;deal with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7280853&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:dbc271c6a37f1f7f89c8f6ceae38e912:1&#34;&gt;the &lt;code&gt;tail&lt;/code&gt; command is used to print the last lines of a text file. &lt;code&gt;tail -f server_log&lt;/code&gt; is a knee-jerk reaction to any server issue.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:dbc271c6a37f1f7f89c8f6ceae38e912:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:dbc271c6a37f1f7f89c8f6ceae38e912:2&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;wq&lt;/code&gt; saves a files in vim and closes the text editor
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:dbc271c6a37f1f7f89c8f6ceae38e912:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evan Priestly on PHP</title>
      <link>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-05-25-evan-priestly-on-php/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-05-25-evan-priestly-on-php/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Facebook, I described myself as &amp;ldquo;the engineer who hates PHP the least&amp;rdquo; and have also been called a &amp;ldquo;PHP idiot savant&amp;rdquo;. While I&amp;rsquo;m not really a fan of PHP, my understanding of it is extremely deep so there&amp;rsquo;s a huge activation energy for me to learn something else. I also think language choice is far less important than most people make it out to be; in my experience, the people who I have encountered who scoff the hardest at PHP and cry the most loudly about the importance of languages tend to also be really bad at doing any useful work in the languages they advocate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evan Priestly via &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quora.com/How-did-Evan-Priestley-learn-to-program&#34;&gt;Quora&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming is Hard</title>
      <link>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-02-07-programming-is-hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-02-07-programming-is-hard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When Joe Armstrong, the creator of Erlang, &lt;a href=&#34;http://joearms.github.io/2014/02/07/why-programming-is-difficult.html&#34;&gt;writes a post&lt;/a&gt; on &amp;ldquo;Programming is Hard&amp;rdquo; you cant help but say to yourself - You&amp;rsquo;re not alone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve got this far, you’ll understand that I think programming is pretty damn difficult. That’s why workplaces are designed to make programming even more difficult. We have open plan offices which provide a noisy environment to break our concentration, mobile phones to disturb us, and internet to distract us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, one cant help but wonder at the power we, programmers, have - power to automate mundane tasks, solve hard problems and hopefully to change the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S: To generate this new post, I hacked up a quick &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/prakhar1989/prakhar1989.github.com/blob/master/Rakefile&#34;&gt;Rakefile&lt;/a&gt; to create a new post and dev environment for me. Yay for automation (&amp;amp; laziness)!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantity</title>
      <link>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-02-10-quantity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-02-10-quantity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ceramics teacher announced on opening day that he was dividing the class into two groups. All those on the left side of the studio, he said, would be graded solely on the quantity of work they produced, all those on the right solely on its quality. His procedure was simple: on the final day of class he would bring in his bathroom scales and weigh the work of the “quantity” group: fifty pound of pots rated an “A”, forty pounds a “B”, and so on. Those being graded on “quality”, however, needed to produce only one pot — albeit a perfect one — to get an “A”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, came grading time and a curious fact emerged: the works of highest quality were all produced by the group being graded for quantity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems that while the “quantity” group was busily churning out piles of work — and learning from their mistakes — the “quality” group had sat theorizing about perfection, and in the end had little more to show for their efforts than grandiose theories and a pile of dead clay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/dp/B0042JSQLU/&#34;&gt;Art and Fear&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thinking For Programmers</title>
      <link>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-04-05-thinking-for-programmers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-04-05-thinking-for-programmers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Leslie Lamport, the creator the famous Paxos&amp;rsquo; Algorithm and LaTeX, in his paper talks about what programmers are doing wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer: Not thinking enough&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
For quite a while, I’ve been disturbed by the emphasis on language in computer science. One result of that emphasis is programmers who are C++ experts but can’t write programs that do what they’re supposed to. The typical computer science response is that programmers need to use the right programming/specification/development language instead of/in addition to C++. The typical industrial response is to provide the programmer with better debugging tools, on the theory that we can obtain good programs by putting a monkey at a keyboard and automatically finding the errors in its code.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the accompanying &lt;a href=&#34;http://channel9.msdn.com/Events/Build/2014/3-642&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why We Dont Sell Ads</title>
      <link>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-02-20-why-we-dont-sell-ads/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-02-20-why-we-dont-sell-ads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I found this great statement made by the WhatsApp founders on their blog about why they don&amp;rsquo;t rely on ads and instead charge customers for the service. This is getting recirculated now that WhatsApp is looking at being acquired by Facebook at a valuation of around $19B. It interesting to see that while tons of apps rely on advertising as a key part of their business model there are companies who strive to go against it. Whats surprising is that their experience of working at an advertising behemoth, Yahoo, strengthened their resolve even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Advertising isn’t just the disruption of aesthetics, the insults to your intelligence and the interruption of your train of thought. At every company that sells ads, a significant portion of their engineering team spends their day tuning data mining, writing better code to collect all your personal data, upgrading the servers that hold all the data and making sure it’s all being logged and collated and sliced and packaged and shipped out … And at the end of the day the result of it all is a slightly different advertising banner in your browser or on your mobile screen.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, when advertising is involved you the user are the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At WhatsApp, our engineers spend all their time fixing bugs, adding new features and ironing out all the little intricacies in our task of bringing rich, affordable, reliable messaging to every phone in the world. That’s our product and that’s our passion. Your data isn’t even in the picture. We are simply not interested in any of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.whatsapp.com/index.php/2012/06/why-we-dont-sell-ads/&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Write Code Everyday</title>
      <link>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-04-10-write-code-everyday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://192.241.186.225/articles/2014-04-10-write-code-everyday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important to note that that I don’t particularly care about the outward perception of the above Github chart. I think that’s the most important take away from this experiment: this is about a change that you’re making in your life for yourself not a change that you’re making to satisfy someone else’s perception of your work. The same goes for any form of dieting or exercise: if you don’t care about improving yourself then you’ll never actually succeed. - John Resig&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its inspiring to read about how programming greats like &lt;a href=&#34;http://ejohn.org&#34;&gt;John Resig&lt;/a&gt; are struggling with working on side projects and the changes they make to their lifestyle in order to push something meaningful each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think no matter how experienced or productive one is as a programmer, each of us struggles with the same issues of feeling lazy, bored and occasionally too burnt out to code. What&amp;rsquo;s motivated me most after the post is the fact that if John Resig can work this hard to write code each day so should I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently on a 20 day streak github, which is the highest I&amp;rsquo;ve been on this far. Working on &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/a85/newman&#34;&gt;newman&lt;/a&gt; has been both fun and challenging to keep me engaged for 3 weeks. I&amp;rsquo;m quite anxious on how I will keep up the streak post the release but as John says, the important point is to make a change in yourself for something that you care about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you who haven&amp;rsquo;t read the blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://ejohn.org/blog/write-code-every-day/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;d strongly encourage you to do so!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>