<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Inspiration on cat /dev/random</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/inspiration/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Inspiration on cat /dev/random</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2014 12:34:58 AST</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/inspiration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Just Learn</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/articles/just-learn/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2014 12:34:58 AST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/articles/just-learn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So strangely enough the optimal thing do to in college if you want to be a successful startup founder is not some sort of new, vocational version of college focused on &amp;ldquo;entrepreneurship.&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s the classic version of college as education for its own sake. If you want to start a startup after college, what you should do in college is learn powerful things. And if you have genuine intellectual curiosity, that&amp;rsquo;s what you&amp;rsquo;ll naturally tend to do if you just follow your own inclinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The component of entrepreneurship that really matters is domain expertise. The way to become Larry Page was to become an expert on search. And the way to become an expert on search was to be driven by genuine curiosity, not some ulterior motive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its best, starting a startup is merely an ulterior motive for curiosity. And you&amp;rsquo;ll do it best if you introduce the ulterior motive toward the end of the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here is the ultimate advice for young would-be startup founders, boiled down to two words: &lt;strong&gt;just learn.&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;http://paulgraham.com/before.html&#34;&gt;Paul Graham&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Do You Want To Do Great Things?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/articles/why-do-you-want-to-do-great-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2014 12:34:58 AST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/articles/why-do-you-want-to-do-great-things/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do you want to do great things? Seriously, dig into it. When I ask a lot of people in startups this question and dig long enough, it comes down to money&amp;ndash; they want to be rich, they want to be free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fact: I&amp;rsquo;ve met these rich/free people and they are largely working their asses off to get more rich (and presumably more free?). The ones who make it (largely) LOVE THE GAME. The few who get rich somehow but don&amp;rsquo;t actually love the game of getting rich are listlessly complaining about being unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t love the game, it seems. &lt;strong&gt;The way to be happy/satisfied is to find the game that you love or learn to love the game you&amp;rsquo;re playing. The latter is often what to focus on&amp;ndash; there people with much less interesting jobs that are satisfied with them.&lt;/strong&gt; Whatever job you have, figure out how to be freakin&amp;rsquo; awesome at it and opportunities fall into your lap- trust me. Or be the guy who gets by, can&amp;rsquo;t be happy, is always looking out the window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that said, don&amp;rsquo;t settle for a shitty job. Get one where you&amp;rsquo;re surrounded by people who impress you in an industry/market that has potential. That&amp;rsquo;s where you&amp;rsquo;ll find your next co-founder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve got great ideas, start side projects. They turn into businesses all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reduce your burn rate ruthlessly and save $. Seriously, your car/house/clothes are too nice, and you have them because society makes you feel less successful if you don&amp;rsquo;t. Happiness and stuff have virtually no correlation. Get to the point where you&amp;rsquo;re downright smug about your burn rate. Smirk at people who drive BMWs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that a million years of evolution has made humanity naturally discontent&amp;ndash; do you think happiness/contentedness is a survival trait? Add to that the external pressure of peers who make it big, do &amp;ldquo;great things&amp;rdquo;, and the river of marketing telling you that you need fancier watches, shinier cars, the newest iPhone. &lt;strong&gt;Being happy/content takes smarts and discipline that most people simply can&amp;rsquo;t manage. Be one of the ones who can&lt;/strong&gt;. - Tony Wright via &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8177830&#34;&gt;HN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I love HN.  Do checkout the rest of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8177259&#34;&gt;discussion&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Mature Engineer</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/articles/being-a-senior-engineer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 12:34:58 AST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/articles/being-a-senior-engineer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kitchensoap.com/2012/10/25/on-being-a-senior-engineer/&#34;&gt;Brilliant article&lt;/a&gt; on what differentiates senior engineers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Every successful engineer I’ve met, upon finishing up a design or getting ready for a project, will continually ask their peers questions along the lines of:

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What could I be missing?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How will this not work?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Will you please shoot as many holes as possible into my thinking on this?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Even if it’s technically sound, is it understandable enough for the rest of the organization to operate, troubleshoot, and extend it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; This is because they know that nothing they make will ever only be in their hands, and that good peer review is what makes better design decisions. As it’s been said elsewhere, they “beg for the bad news.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Excuses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/articles/2014-05-31-no-excuses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/articles/2014-05-31-no-excuses/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stop-making-excuses-go-build-something:6447788d8c683d544fb0e6be3bdae629&#34;&gt;Stop Making Excuses. Go Build Something&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is, that you can and should teach yourself some new skills. You’re way closer to being employable than I was, that’s for sure. It may take some evenings and weekends, but they’ll be some of the most fun evening and weekends you ever have. Find something that you want to do and build it. Fall in love with the idea, but be ready to dump it for something better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;via &lt;a href=&#34;http://scottpatten.ca/2012/04/no-excuses.html&#34;&gt;Scott Patten&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>